Britain's historic royal [music]
palaces, those no longer in use by the
royal family, are some of the finest,
best preserved, [music] and most studied
pieces of architecture in Europe.
But these [music] are not buildings of
lifeless stone.
Look beyond the battlements and scratch
away the guilt [music] and you'll find
signs of life everywhere.
Etchings and scratchings of lovers
[music] and prisoners, kings and kitchen
boys, the finger marks of the everyday
lives lived [music] in these buildings
for a thousand years.
>> [music]
[music]
>> The oldest of the historic palaces is
the Tower of London.
[music] For over 900 years, a palace, a
royal mint, and a prison.
In the Beum Tower, there are signs of
over 90 desperate lives simply etched
onto the walls.
These are the lasting momento of 8,000
prisoners that are known to have been
held in the tower between 1100 [music]
and 1941.
Some on their way to freedom, some on
their way to the tower's infamous block
and axe.
James Spooner is a creator with the
bright idea of making copies of the
graffiti long since protected behind
glass that can be touched and traced by
visitors to this eerie cell. Jane's job
is to stage the exhibition. Karen
Harris's job is to protect the historic
graffiti.
>> The graffiti is a is an important part
of that story obviously because it's
what people did when they were kept in
the beach and tower. So, we're proposing
to make [music] some replicas and um
really I'd like your advice on what we
can and can't do.
>> Jane has chosen [music] three pieces to
copy. Perhaps the smallest is the best
known, her namesake, Lady Jane Gray, the
9-day queen. One prisoner, one life
among many.
held in these rooms at the age of 16
[music] from where she saw the cart
returning from Tower Hill with the body
of her young husband and the block and
axe arranged that would take her life.
Each piece of graffiti is a [music]
moment in time. A cry from the past and
Karen's job is [music] to be sure we
hand them on as we find them.
>> Yes, do think bloody hell. [music] But I
also think okay this is a challenge. We
are basically here to make sure that the
objects in our care are accessible to
the public whilst at the same time
preserving them for future generations.
So we do have to come up with a plan. If
it's too fragile, if it's too
implausible, then yes, we will say no.
For nearly a thousand years, the kings,
courtortiers, and hundreds of ordinary
people living in the tower have thrown
their rubbish into the temps.
Every year, for 2 days only, the tower
opens up the foreshore to historical
treasure hunters of all ages.
The event attracts its regulars. Dawn
may have spent more time exploring this
river than anyone else alive.
He never misses these rare opportunities
to get onto this exclusive stretch of
riverbed.
>> Blammy is here again.
>> Once the tide is retreated, Dawn is
ready for action.
>> I would like to find what I found before
last a little pilgrim badge. I I like a
filing badge because
poor buggers like me could afford it.
>> But Don won't have the beach to himself.
Paul is also a sharpeyed beach coma.
>> This annual event is always popular. So,
there can be serious competition.
>> That's good. Might be lucky today cuz
this part I'm going to now was barred
last year.
I found something nice there and
somebody else did.
Let's see what I can find now.
>> [music]
>> much more.
>> But Hall is the first to make a decent
find.
>> So, what have you found there?
>> I think that it's chain mail. And I'm
wondering if this is perhaps from a
factory that made it at the tower. Hard
to say until we show it to somebody else
again.
>> Yeah.
>> However, Don is having less luck.
large iron wash of probably something on
a ship I should imagine but rubbish
>> prisoners which are being featured in
>> Karen has called in Matthew Nation.
>> He specializes in copying from stone by
applying a resin that sets hard and
forms a mold.
Karen's worry is that the resin will
damage her centuries old graffiti.
>> This is the graffiti.
>> I'm not convinced. I'm not sure. Yes, I
think it's going to work brilliantly.
[laughter]
Sorry. He was going like this. Yes.
I don't know.
>> Matthew applies a resin to a [music]
test patch a few inches away from the
precious carvings.
>> You seem quite relaxed about this so
far. It's not obvious signs of your
career going up in smoke.
>> No. No. Not yet. [music] Not yet.
The alternatives to this sticky option
are to abandon the project altogether or
to call in high techch [music]
specialists and the ultramodern art of
laser copying. It's an art form that's
still in its infancy, unpredictable and
expensive. But before any decisions are
taken, everyone is going to have to wait
to see if these sticky [music] patches
leave a mark.
The tide is bringing the beach comb to
an end and Dawn has had no luck. But
there's always tomorrow.
>> It's the second and final day the public
will be allowed onto the tower
foreshore. But though the beach is not
yet open, a lone figure has sidestepped
the authorities and is already at work.
>> Dawn has got down there.
>> Yes.
>> Yeah. Don. Oh yeah, he's
>> sneak.
>> First find
>> the early bird they say catches the
word.
>> Hammered silver penny.
>> So how old do you think this is? Tuda.
>> Bit of magic. Yeah. If there's nothing
else there all day, I'll beat the
American now for this this alone. Yeah,
>> I think Don's getting quietly
competitive down the far end.
>> Yeah, well, Don's the master though.
There's no competition with Don.
>> Me away cuz I've got to show I've got to
show off now. Rock,
>> you better show off.
>> Be very rare. Look at that. Look at
that.
>> It's a It's a long cross. It's a Groat,
isn't it?
>> Well, I don't know if it's a Groat or a
penny, but very very rare. Amazing.
Wonderful.
>> Isn't that nice? Yes.
>> Wow.
[laughter]
>> So, we're both found this time.
>> Good. Good.
>> His day's work done. Don concentrates on
his role as forshore celebrity.
But the American has time for one
[music] more find. The cow trough. It
was made. They would throw them on the
ground and the horse would stand on that
and it would go into the soft part of
the foot and who uh the horse would
collapse and be useless and all they
could do was slaughter him and eat the
meat. And the cow shop was like a it was
like the things that the the police in
America throw down the
>> throw around in order to
>> No matter which way you throw it
>> the point up.
>> Yes. I've never seen one before. I never
thought.
>> So God bless you Paul.
I've got a hot
>> beck
in the water.
>> In the Beum Tower, the test patches are
carefully removed. It's important for
Karen that they come away from the
historic stone without leaving any stain
whatsoever.
>> Normally, you would take that one off
almost instantly.
>> Yeah.
>> Not exactly invisible.
We've got two here. We got the first one
which we
>> Once the patches are removed, Jane's
keen to review the results.
>> Will it be cheap and sticky or high tech
and expensive?
>> These two have a residue and it's not
possible to clean that off.
>> We could probably clean it off more than
we have done already. I thought I'd
leave it like this for you to see it.
>> Um
>> I'm not very happy with those.
>> My feeling is I'm not very happy with it
and I think we should look into
>> Yeah. Seeing if we can find the money
and use the laser option.
>> Bit pricey though.
>> Yes. Bit pricey. See if we can
see if we can find the money.
>> Yeah. Okay. It's very important to
preserve and treasure what we have and
um if we can't afford to do that then we
shouldn't do anything at all really. So
we're going to um do a little bit of
investigating to see if we can find the
funding to do to use the right method to
make the replicas of the graffiti. And
if we can't find the funding, then um
I'm going to recommend that we don't do
it.
>> Hampton Court is known the world over as
the power base of Henry VIII, the great
Tuda Palace.
The House of Stewart was based here,
developing the gardens and bringing
Shakespeare to perform in the great
hall. The House of Hanover extended the
palace before cooling to its charms and
abandoning it finally forever.
But for those who look carefully, there
are signs of more recent lives
everywhere.
They're on the walls and in the
cloysters, in the alleyways and
stairwells, and they tell a story that
has haunted Sarah Parker for 5 years.
Everybody assumes that kings and queens
lived at Hampton Court Palace, but
actually there's a little known fact
that Grace and Favor residents lived in
the palace from about the middle of the
18th century for roughly about 200 to
250 years. Now they were um generally
widows of distinguished servicemen and
as a result were given free
accommodation actually inside the
palace. I suppose when I discovered that
the Grace and Favor residents lived here
and I wanted to know who they were and
why they lived here, it did become I
guess bordering on an obsession for me
and it's sort of my mission really to
tell people that story.
>> Sarah's dream is to stage an exhibition
about the Grace and Favor residents at
Hampton Court.
Before she can submit her proposal,
Sarah's beginning the serious task of
researching the exhibition by tracking
down as many people as possible with
personal memories of the Grace and Favor
Ladies.
>> Oh, look, the name's still there.
>> Yes.
>> Any
put in there?
>> Well, potatoes, [music]
uh, cauliflowers.
There we go. It's very old.
>> Fantastic. Well done. Oh, that's
wonderful that it works.
>> I did really feel at home here. It was
beautiful. I mean, I explored the whole
of the palace. I think went up to the
above the clock there, climbed all the
way up. [music] Things that we probably
shouldn't have done, but we had that
sort of freedom living here. It was
wonderful.
>> I just love wandering through the empty
apartments in the palace. This is um
nursery wallpaper and it shows the story
of um Gilpin. Away went Gilpin and away
he went postboy at his hills. The post
boy's horse right glad to miss the
lumbering of the wheels. And it shows
the entire story which is a very popular
story.
[music]
But at that time we would take our
coffee break um with a thermos flask and
we weren't allowed to sit on any of the
benches because it was a very cold and
we were down here [music] by ourselves.
We did sit long and I found the ladies
came more comfortable
that
>> the grace and favors practically ran the
palace at one time. It was their home
[music] and they always described it as
being like a a village
>> because they all knew each other and
6:00 was drinks time and that was it.
>> At the tower, there's an expectant air.
Today, the Bechum Tower is closed to the
public. The 16th century graffiti
trapped behind glass is being liberated
at last thanks to modern technology.
This technology can scan the graffiti in
three dimensions without anything
actually touching the precious
artifacts. No contact, no damage. Then
the information can be used to reproduce
the etchings perfectly. At least that's
the promise.
Across Tower Green stands the bloody
tower. This is where the little princes
are said to have been murdered on the
orders of Richard III.
Current conservation work has revealed a
new sign of the lives uncovered in this
tower. Marks have been found that seem
to defy an explanation.
Jane has called in Lee Proser. Lee has
been making a study of strange markings.
>> Okay. So, they're bits on this um this
door here.
>> All right.
>> Ooh.
>> Okay. So, these are what I was wondering
about.
>> And these have only just been noticed,
have they?
>> The door is usually flat back against
the wall. So, it it actually hasn't been
seen in this way for quite a long time,
really. Right. It's always worth having
a look at these very odd marks on doors
and things like that.
>> Now the question is what do these marks
mean? These marks are usually confined
to particular places and those places
are doors. Um they are mantel pieces,
they are roof timbers close to windows
and chimneys and they are on buildings
of a particular date as well. And it's
no coincidence that that period is one
of quite um heightened superstition
about the fear of witches and that kind
of thing. It's the late 16th to the late
17th century. It's the time of the Salem
witch trials and people are hysterical
about witches and they really believed
at that time that there were witches
about and witches could come into your
house and um and put a curse on you or
bewitch you. So they made these marks,
we think, as a way of warding off that
that potential evil.
>> On her searches of the Lost Grayson
Favor Apartments of Hampton Court, Sarah
has also made an unexpected discovery.
>> If I just turn these over. Oh, isn't
that beautiful?
>> Well, I found three boxes relating to
the Manning family who were the last
occupants of apartment 23.
Hello.
>> Oh, hello. It's Sarah Parker from
Hampton Court Palace. We spoke a couple
of days ago. I just remember you telling
me that at the time after your mother um
had died, you put various things aside
that as part of the sort of family
archive heirloom of of books and
photographs and and all that sort of
thing. Um I think I may have found them.
>> Oh, I found three different boxes.
>> Lady Northbrook and Mrs. Dora Roy are
the daughters of Lady Manning, among the
select few who can claim to have grown
up in Hampton Court Palace. [laughter]
>> Today they've come to see if the box of
photographs really is theirs.
>> So I mean they are your family, I take
it.
>> That does look like Al. I have no idea
what's on the back. Olga.
>> Oh, that is that's my mother. Our
mother.
>> [music]
>> The old pictures awaken memories of a
very unusual childhood.
>> No, it was fun. I think really used to
take my [music] dog into into the home
park. We used to chase chase the sheep.
It was quite embarrassing. No, it's a
lovely place to live really, but
restricted if you were a child, you
know. We had quite jolly parties, lovely
dinner parties.
>> And you mentioned Lady Bum Pa earlier.
Was she sort of a jolly old lady?
>> Um, well, she was rightfully busy with
the girl guides the whole time. Very.
>> Do you remember the time when she went
away and left us with two two pigeon two
two dumps in a cage? Yes.
>> And [laughter] they were rather randy
dumps. Do you remember
>> kept on falling off the perches or fluff
of feathers? But I know we had some
butters belonging to somebody too.
>> Was that the same thing?
>> Storm.
>> Thank you for the photograph.
>> Bye.
>> Bye. It was great. It's just
fascinating. Who could ask for anything
better really? I could be working in an
office somewhere in central London, but
I don't. I work at Hampton Court Palace.
[music]
Jane and Karen have traveled to the
conservation center in Liverpool to see
the cast [music] results of the laser
scan.
Though some of the statues being worked
on are centuries [music] old, Jane's
only interested in her brand new
graffiti.
>> It's not what she was expecting.
>> It's a bit of a shock seeing them like
this um as opposed to with its original
color and on the in situ. And so
>> that sort of color adds a huge dimension
especially as it's been highlighted.
>> I mean it looks a bit like a pixelated
effect.
>> This is the next step. Hand finishing
>> right
>> is where that kind of thing will be
removed.
>> Oh right. Fantastic. Great. [laughter]
>> So
slightly worried.
>> We're basically we're basically two
twothirds of the way through
>> Yes.
>> the process.
>> We want people to be able to touch it
and especially people who can't actually
see properly to be able to touch it, but
also we do want it to look convincing as
>> as the real thing as well.
>> But as Jane and Karen are about to
discover, this is just the beginning of
the possibilities of laser scanning.
>> We've got a device here called the
Phantom Desktop. So with this device,
which is basically a modeling pen, I can
actually go in to the model. This is a
three-dimensional model. I can turn it
around
and if I put up a side camera, if you
like, I can touch the object and you can
just Yes, you can feel it.
>> Just touch the
>> Oh gosh,
>> that's it. As you as you would with to
its original state. It's it's really
bizarre because it's you know you know
in your in your mind that it's it's you
know it's only a two-dimensional image
but you can feel exactly where
>> where the three-dimensional
>> and the more you use the shadows are
more here you're actually connecting
through your sense of touch
>> people can actually get a sense a of
touching the object but b actually doing
the conservation as it were
>> engaging actually pulling the layers
off. Michelangelo would have loved to be
able to use this. [laughter]
>> I tell you, I mean,
>> that's fabulous. I want one.
>> Well, it's in development, shall we say?
[laughter]
It's
>> It's virtual conservation. You can see
what effect you're going to have to an
object before you actually do it.
>> It's a very exciting technology. Yes, it
[music] has huge potential.
Q Palace has been closed to the public
for almost 10 years. It stands in Q
Gardens, shutters closed against [music]
the famous greenery.
This is where George III was brought
while he was said to be insane.
This is where they strapped him and kept
him away from his court.
Over 200 years on, the palace still
feels like it has secrets hidden away.
Following the discovery of the
mysterious witch marks in the Tower of
London, Lee has come to explore the
attic [music] where witch marks are
known to exist.
>> Palace has been closed for
8 [music] years. So, it's just been like
this really. It's sad. I don't I don't
think a building should be like that. A
building needs to be looked lived in.
Lived in in the sense of being [music]
used to ensure its survival.
But there's a plan to [music] reawaken
the sleeping palace. A6 million pound
project is about to begin to reopen the
building and breathe new life into its
[music] fading grandeur. For now though,
Lee remains one of the privileged few
with a key.
The floor we're going up to is quite
special because it's never been open to
the public before. The other the other
two floors were um open in the 1960s and
up to the '9s, but this floor is a bit
like Cinderella floor. It's it's it's
been left completely
untouched almost for [music] two nearly
200 years. And the last people who
stayed in these rooms were the royal
princesses [music] in the 1810s.
And when Queen Charlotte died, the
palace was mothball and it was never
lived in again. They're just fantastic
um time capsules of what life was
[music] like for these princesses. And
we're going to open this again. We're
going to bring it back and um certainly
um show [music] these rooms to the
public for the first time.
But it's the attic that Lee has really
come to explore. Home of the witch or
apotropeic marks. [music]
The best one of all is on this on this
uh collar here which goes across from
these two big big [music] oak um
rafters. And what you can see here is a
sort of circle with these rays coming
away from it if you like. But this is
just just fantastic. There's there's no
other explanation for it. Everyone's
heard of the stories of witches being
ducked in ponds and that kind of thing.
And that was all occurring at just the
[music] time when this house was being
built. So the dating of these marks is
absolutely right for that period where
there's there's mass [music] hysteria
about, you know, witches.
For me, it's the most it's the treasure
of the house, this door. Look at this.
It's fantastic.
And this this pull, this is original to
1631. It's never been replaced. I mean,
how often would you get that? Well, most
people don't know, but that's the sort
of thing. Oh, get rid of it. Hack it
off. But here we've got the original
pull. It's the the door is just so rare
and it's been riveted
and scribed with crosses as well. Maybe
that's some other protective thing. Oh,
here's another. Now, here's here's an
Aperture paint mark. I haven't seen
actually. I haven't seen this at all.
That's fantastic.
Look at that.
There's one I missed. And it's it's
really clear. It's an M
and there's just the tail of what looks
like an R. So again, that that is a an
it's invoking the Blessed Virgin Mary to
protect the house against evil spirits.
They're made of the same kind of tool
that the others are made of. And this is
why I think that they're all related.
They obviously did their job cuz there's
no witches in the house.
It's all part of the rich tapestry of
history, isn't it? I mean, those are the
sorts of things people were concerned
with. They should they give us an
insight into the [music] minds of people
in those days, particularly the less
well educated people, the people who
lived in the roof for whom, you know, we
don't have their names, but we have
something of their beliefs in these
Don and Paul have scrubbed up well and
have come to the Museum of London to
show curator Hazel Forsythe their
foreshore discoveries.
>> This is a silver coin. It it has a sort
of tarnished appearance and the edges
are very araided. Um it's actually quite
thin because it was a a fairly low
denomination coin. It's a half gout
worth about two pennies. You've got a
profile bust of Henry VIIth.
>> That's it.
>> With his crown. And then just to the
right of the crown, the very top
incorporated in the legend is the Port
Calis. And the Port Cullis is the Tower
Mint Mark.
>> Yeah.
>> So, we know that it was made in London,
issued in London.
>> And the Tower of London, um, as you
know, was both a citadel, Royal Palace,
>> and the seat of the the mint, as well as
many other things. Paul, what's that
you've got in your hand? It looks very
intriguing.
>> We've been finding for the last 3 years
at the tower, we've been finding chain
mail or what certainly appears to be
chain mail.
>> That's indeed what it is, but it's
actually quite beautiful. And one of the
great advantages of it is its
flexibility
>> and comparative lightweight. And then
the fact that we found it in a similar
place each year at the tower kind of
down near the end closer to the bridge
>> really makes me wonder if there's a
chance that that would have been around
the place where workshops might have
been or if if it could have just been
where you know sweepings would have
gone.
>> That's very probable. And I think the
foreshore objects very often pose more
questions than we are able to answer. So
even though these things appear to be
sort of inconsequential very often in
isolation, taken as a whole, they're
incredibly important.
>> Sarah's initial research is complete and
there's news from on high.
>> Actually, very good news. I've been
trying to get the palace to put on an
exhibition on the grace and favor
residence for a long time and it's
actually come through. We're going to
put on an exhibition and it will
hopefully be opening um in March 2005.
>> The palaces are a patchwork of the lives
played out in their closters and
corridors. Lives that shaped history
alongside lives quickly forgotten.
Sarah's exhibition will celebrate a few
of those lives, each a part of the great
pageant of British history. Another
exhibition closer to completion is being
installed at last in the Tower of
London.
>> When we last saw them, they were just
simply white carved blocks and uh
[clears throat] they hadn't been
handfinished at all. So, the big change
really is that they're much more
accurately carved because they were they
were handfinished with sculptor's tools.
[music] I think it's looking really good
already and it's really nice seeing it
all come together. Right. Is that lined
up?
Heat.
[music]
I hate myself.
>> [music]